I’ve been working as a football journalist for 24 years
我做足球记者24年了
and I’ve covered all kinds of stories.
报道过各种各样的故事
But what happened on December 18th
但是12月18日发生的事情
is the greatest pure sports story
是我报道过的最伟大的纯粹的体育故事
My name’s Eli Mengem and for the past few years
我叫Eli Mengem，过去几年
I’ve been traversing Europe, documenting the tales
我一直在欧洲各地旅行
of football clubs and their fanbases
记录那些足球俱乐部和球迷的故事
who’ve been on the verge of winning something
他们即将赢得一些荣誉
for the first time in a long time.
这是很久以来的第一次…
If not ever.
甚至永远不会
From Northern Turkey
从土耳其北部
to Southern Spain.
到西班牙南部
From South West Germany
从德国西南部
to the Basque country.
到巴斯克地区
I’ve been on a mission to show how important it is
我一直在努力展示一件重要的事
that the game has a variety of winners
这项运动需要不同的获胜者
So that we learn about new places.
这样我们就能了解新的地方
New people.
新的人们
New cultures and most importantly
新的文化，最重要的是
new stories.
新的故事
Then came the 2022 FIFA World Cup.
然后是2022年FIFA世界杯
Where I knew the exact “Once In A Lifetime” story I had to tell.
我清楚地知道我必须讲述的“一生一次”的故事
So as the world’s media descended on Qatar
当全世界的媒体都涌向卡塔尔
to be at the tournament.
报道比赛时
COPA90 and I decided to fly 8000 miles in the opposite direction
COPA90和我决定飞往8000英里外的相反方向
to tell the ultimate story of a football fanbase
去讲述一个足球球迷群体的终极故事
on the brink of ending a 36 year wait
他们即将结束36年的等待
for the biggest prize in sport.
为了赢得这项运动中最大的奖项
But what we found we found was a story that transcended football.
但我们发现的是一个超越足球的故事
A story that reached into the very soul of a nation
一个触及国家灵魂的故事
that laid itself bare over two fateful weeks.
这个国家在决定性的两周里毫无保留地展现了自己
A story that etched a struggle for identity in a search for glory
这是一个关于身份斗争的故事
that began over two centuries ago...
始于两个多世纪前的荣耀追寻
A story about Lionel Messi.
一个关于Lionel Messi的故事
Argentina.
关于阿根廷
And 45 million people yearning to reclaim their place in history.
关于4500万人渴望重新夺回他们在历史中的位置
This is the all angle,
这是全方位的
on the ground, as it happened
在现场，实时记录的
ultimate account
终极叙述
of perhaps the greatest football story of our time
这或许是我们时代最伟大的足球故事
Back in Buenos Aires, hungover but at least not jet-lagged
回到布宜诺斯艾利斯，宿醉但至少没有时差
we’d returned to a city
我们回到了一个基本上
basically running on World Cup hype.
靠世界杯热情运行的城市
Where all anyone was wearing...
那里所有人都穿着...
All anyone was watching...
所有人都在观看
All anyone was reading...
所有人都在阅读
Or all anyone was reading, whilst watching...
或者所有人都在阅读，同时观看
was World Cup related.
都与世界杯有关
So to get a grasp of the situation, naturally
所以，为了掌握情况，自然地
we obeyed the Cabalas
我们遵守了Cabalas（指的是人们相信的、能带来好运或坏运的各种“迷信”）
and started our World Cup Final countdown
并开始了我们的世界杯决赛倒计时
by catching up with Santi
通过与Santi联系
who wore the exact same shirt
他穿着完全一样的衬衫
and insisted on speaking in the exact same spot.
并坚持在完全相同的地方讲话
Welcome back to the bench!
欢迎回到板凳席！
The Cabalas bench!
Cabalas替补席
One more!
再来一次
For the third and final time! Yes!
第三次也是最后一次，是的
And whilst there was a lot to talk about
虽然有很多事情要谈
there was one particular subject we had to start with.
但有一个特别的话题我们必须先谈
It’s funny we came here obviously to tell this story
有趣的是，我们显然是来这里讲述这个故事的
“Once In A Lifetime” hoping, but...
“一生一次” 希望如此 但……
I didn’t think there was anyway we could have had this many
我认为我们不可能有这么多
magical Messi moments in particular.
尤其是梅西的神奇时刻
Magical Messi moments.
梅西的神奇时刻
He is equal top goalscorer
他是并列最佳射手
Most assists.
最多助攻
Most chances created.
创造最多机会
Most dribbles.
最多盘带
Everyones been talking about how he needs a tournament
每个人都在谈论他需要一个锦标赛
where he grabs the...
在那里他抓住了
World Cup by the scruff of it’s neck...
世界杯的脖颈
like Diego did.
就像Diego那样
And he’s achieving all this at the age of 35.
而他现在35岁了
You can’t forget about that.
你不能忘记这一点
But, no one was forgetting.
但是，没有人忘记
With even the notoriously demanding Argentinian media
即使是臭名昭著的苛刻阿根廷媒体
gushing in their praise.
也在滔滔不绝地赞扬他
“THIS MESSI HAS ME FASCINATEDHOW COULD I CRITICISE HIM?”
“这个Messi让我着迷，我怎么能批评他？”
Best summed up by the words of reporter Sofia Martinez
记者Sofia Martinez的话最能概括这一点
who chose not to ask Messi something,
她选择不问Messi什么
but tell him.
而是告诉他
The World Cup Final is coming
世界杯决赛就要来了
and although we'd all like to win it,
虽然我们都想赢
I just wanted to tell you that whatever the result is…..
我只是想告诉你，无论结果如何
there is something that no one can ever take away from you.
有一些东西是没有人能从你身上夺走的
You have touched every single Argentinian.
你感动了每一个阿根廷人
I mean it when I say that.
我是认真的
And so with even the media caught up in the Messi lovefest
因此，即使是媒体也陷入了对Messi的喜爱
I caught up with journalist Joel Richards to find out more.
我采访了记者Joel Richards以了解更多信息
I thought it was really moving and really touching
我觉得这真的很感人，很动人
I thought, she said what everyone was thinking.
我想，她说出了每个人都在想的事情
I mean he is the one who is making us all dream...
我的意思是，是他让我们所有人都在做梦
who is getting us so optimistic and hopeful.
是他让我们如此乐观和充满希望
And in every walk of life, in every social interaction,
在生活的方方面面，在每一次社会交往中
people are lighter on their feet,
人们的脚步都轻快了
they’re happier, they’re smiling.
他们更快乐了，他们在微笑
And that’s not something that always comes hand in hand with Argentines.
而这并不是总是与阿根廷人相伴相随的东西
That’s not the stereotype.
这不是刻板印象
You see the ubiquitous optimism we were coming across
你看到的普遍乐观情绪，我们遇到的
wasn’t exactly typical of modern Argentinian life.
并非现代阿根廷生活的典型特征
You’ve only been here in Argentina for a week.
你只在阿根廷待了一个星期
You might think people celebrating, chanting, being happy
你可能认为人们庆祝、唱歌、快乐
this is normal.
这很正常
It’s not normal. You know what’s normal?
这不正常，你知道什么是正常的吗
Political turmoil is normal.
政治动荡是正常的
The country’s Vice President was threatened with a gun.
该国副总统受到枪支威胁
Inflation is normal.
通货膨胀是正常的
People in Argentina are struggling
阿根廷人民正在挣扎
with one of the highest inflation rates in the world.
阿根廷是世界上通货膨胀率最高的国家之一
But then the World Cup comes around, Messi shines
但世界杯来了，Messi闪耀
and now you’ve got people standing on top of rooftops and buses.
现在你看到人们站在屋顶和公共汽车顶上
Each day a new viral video came out documenting
每天都会出现新的病毒式传播的视频，记录着
the unbelievable World Cup effect on the country.
世界杯对这个国家令人难以置信的影响
From the goal reactions in the airport and on Argentinian flights.
从机场和阿根廷航班上的进球反应
To those suffering from Argentina’s constant power outages.
到那些遭受阿根廷不断停电之苦的人们
Who were then forced to listen outside on car radios.
他们被迫在外面用车载收音机听
It turned out the combination of Argentinian passion and emotions
事实证明，阿根廷人的激情和情感
with long summer days
与漫长的夏日
and a deep, dramatic World Cup run
以及深沉、戏剧性的世界杯赛事相结合
was the perfect recipe for a never ending cycle of mad moments.
是创造永无止境的疯狂时刻的完美秘诀
From heartwarming scenes of generosity
从感人的慷慨场面
to bizarre moments of anarchy
到怪诞的无政府状态时刻
to hilarious acts of passionate stupidity.
到充满激情的愚蠢的滑稽行为
What has he done?
他做了什么
But nothing embodied the magic unfolding
但没有什么比“Abuela”（奶奶）现象更能体现这种神奇的展开了
as much as the ‘Abuela’ (Grandma) phenomenon.
更能体现这种神奇的展开了
Which all began when 76 year old Maria Cristina
这一切都始于76岁的Maria Cristina
joined a post match celebration to the cries of:
加入了赛后的庆祝活动，人们高呼
And so all across the nation any woman of a particular age
因此，在全国各地，任何特定年龄的女性
found themselves being serenaded with:
都会发现自己被歌声包围
In Rosario, they went to Messi’s grandmothers place.
在Rosario，他们去了Messi奶奶家
His old Grandmother’s place!
他的老奶奶家
Just to sing about the fact that she’s the grandmother of Messi.
只是为了歌颂她是Messi的奶奶
This World Cup has not just been a distraction for people.
这届世界杯不仅仅是人们的分心之物
It’s transformed Argentine society.
它改变了阿根廷社会
You’ve got people hanging from traffic lights.
你看到人们挂在交通灯上
You’ve got the elderly kissing on the streets.
你看到老人们在街上接吻
People are happier, it’s that simple.
人们更快乐了，就这么简单
There was a fight that was broken up
一场打架被制止了
because the two people who were fighting were reminded
因为两个打架的人被提醒
that Argentina had won
阿根廷赢了
and had qualified for the final of the World Cup!
并且已经获得了世界杯决赛的资格
"What are you fighting about? We're in the final!”
并且已经获得了世界杯决赛的资格 “你们在吵什么？我们进决赛了！”
I mean this is not normal in Argentina!
我的意思是在阿根廷这不是正常的
This is not normal!
这不是正常的
Spontaneous acts of generosity, happiness
慷慨、幸福的自发行为
that just aren’t things that people are used to hearing about.
这都不是人们习惯听到的事情
There was an old man he was watching the game on the TV
有一个老人，他在商店外面看电视上的比赛
from outside the store.
在商店外面
And now the store has bought the TV for that old man.
现在商店为那个老人买了电视
A wealthy Argentine bought Maradona’s old house.
一个富有的阿根廷人买了Maradona的旧房子
That man, has since, on match days, opened up his house...
从那以后，在比赛日，那个人就打开了房门
put on a barbecue and just let the house fill up with supporters
摆上烧烤，让房子里挤满了球迷
who want to go and be in the place where Maradona lived
人们想去Maradona住过的地方
to watch the game.
看比赛
And that’s just unthinkable, opening up your house to strangers
这简直难以想象，向陌生人敞开你的家门
that’s unthinkable in Argentina...
这在阿根廷是不可想象的
And so many people have been saying
许多人说 如果能把这一周延长就好了
Because everyone’s demeanour,
因为每个人的态度
the way they go about their daily life,
他们日常生活的方式
the way they are at home,
在家中的样子
the way parents are with their children...
父母与孩子相处的方式
has been transformed by Argentina
都因阿根廷进入世界杯决赛而改变
Because this Sunday
因为这个星期天
we’re playing at a World Cup Final for the first time in 8 years.
我们将参加8年来第一次的世界杯决赛
With a chance of winning it for the first time in 36!
有机会在36年后第一次赢得冠军
It's the only joy we can aspire to.
这是我们唯一渴望的快乐
The only one
唯一的
The mood around Argentines has been at an all time low.
阿根廷人的情绪一直处于低谷
We’ve been dealt blow after blow after blow.
我们一次又一次地遭受打击
Historically we've been so screwed by so many governments and...
我们一次又一次地遭受打击 从历史上看，我们被这么多政府搞砸了，而且
and well, it's the joy of the people.
这就是人民的快乐
It's football.
这就是足球
An evasion that allows us some momentary happiness.
一种让我们暂时快乐的逃避
You're crying?
你在哭吗
I get emotional when I talk about Argentina.
当我谈到阿根廷时，我会很激动
But he wasn’t the only one getting emotional
但他不是唯一一个情绪激动的人
at the significance of what it all meant.
这一切的意义
As eventually it even began to dawn on me just what we were a part of.
最终，我开始明白我们参与的是什么
This is all getting too much for me now.
我现在有点受不了了
No more so than when speaking to Maia
尤其是和Maia谈话时
who put it all into context so succinctly.
她把一切都简洁地概括了出来
Our country is going through a complex socio political situation.
她把一切都简洁地概括了出来 我们的国家正在经历复杂的社会政治局势
Yet people are only thinking about winning the World-Cup.
然而，人们只想赢得世界杯
We don't care about anything else.
我们不在乎其他任何事情
People go out to celebrate like they weren't going hungry.
人们出去庆祝，就像他们没有挨饿一样
Like they don't have work problems.
就像他们没有工作问题一样
Like our only concern was to...
就像我们唯一关心的是
celebrate.
庆祝
72 hours until the big final
距离决赛还有72小时
and Argentina had their opponents confirmed.
阿根廷已经确认了他们的对手
The Kylian Mbappe led France.
由Kylian Mbappe带领的法国队
Who were the current World champions
他们是现任世界冠军
and the nation who kicked Argentina out of the last World Cup.
也是在上届世界杯将阿根廷淘汰出局的国家
But whoever we caught up with didn’t seem phased.
但我们遇到的每个人似乎都不为所动
Who cares about Mbappe.
谁在乎Mbappe
We’ve got Messi.
我们有Messi
He makes the whole team play.
我们有Messi 他让整个球队都动了起来
Not only has he scored five goals
他不仅进了五个球
and done three assists
还有三次助攻
he’s become like a manager inside the pitch
他已经成为球场上的教练
for his teammates.
为他的队友们
But this confidence felt deeper than just a belief in Messi.
但这种信心不仅仅是对Messi的信任
Like we say, the planets are aligning for everything to...
就像我们说的，所有的行星都在排列，为了让一切都
become one.
合而为一
Many people are talking about...
合而为一 很多人都在谈论
the coincidences between this World Cup and the one from '86.
这届世界杯和86年世界杯的巧合
There is something curious about it
其中有一些有趣的事情
when Argentina won in ‘86...
当阿根廷在86年夺冠时
he was 17 years old.
他17岁
Right now I am 17 years old.
现在我17岁
The referee for the final was born on the same day as…..
决赛裁判的出生日期是……
different year, but same day as the referee from the '86 final.
年份不同，但和86年决赛的裁判是同一天
And so it came as no surprise
因此，毫不奇怪
the country’s most popular World Cup commercial
国家最流行的世界杯广告
was based around the subject.
就是围绕这个主题展开的
FOR THOSE WHO NEED COINCIDENCES
就是围绕这个主题展开的 对于那些需要巧合的人
THERE ARE COINCIDENCES
巧合是存在的
The final of the 1986 World Cup was played at midday..
1986年世界杯决赛是在中午进行的
and the final in Qatar kicks off at midday!
卡塔尔的决赛也是在中午开始
Once again with the coincidences?
又是巧合吗
Yet for all the talk of fate their superstitious ways continued.
然而，尽管人们都在谈论命运，但他们的迷信方式仍在继续
As I learnt from Vanessa
正如我从Vanessa那里了解到的
a UK born daughter of an Argentinian
一个出生在英国的阿根廷人的女儿
who moved to the country 15 years ago.
15年前移居到这个国家
Like, all these white witches
就像，所有这些白女巫
they’re casting spells,
她们在施法
they’re like writing symbolic numbers
她们就像写象征性的数字
and putting them in the freezers.
把它们放进冰箱里
They’re burying things in the garden.
她们把东西埋在花园里
“La Brujinetas” are a group of witches from Argentina
“La Brujinetas”是来自阿根廷的一群女巫
and what they do is 'spiritually' help the national team.
她们所做的就是“精神上”帮助国家队
It’s like white magic.
这就像白魔法
A group of witches have got together online
这就像白魔法 一群女巫在网上聚在一起
that send the team positive energy.
向球队传递正能量
And you're probably asking really?
你可能会问，真的吗
Yes, really!
是的，真的
In fact even I had created my own Cabalas superstition.
事实上，即使是我也创造了我自己的Cabalas迷信
Too scared to shave my beard in fear of affecting the result.
害怕刮胡子会影响结果
The worst part is it’s Summer so it gets extra itchy
最糟糕的是现在是夏天，所以它会变得格外痒
and extra sweaty
格外汗流浃背
not that you need the details, but...
不是说你需要细节，但是
honestly the things I’m doing just to get this team over the line.
老实说，我正在做的事情只是为了让这支球队越过线
Another day closer to the final
离决赛又近了一天
meant another day of hysterical World Cup moments.
意味着又一天歇斯底里的世界杯时刻
You think it can’t get crazier
你认为它不可能再疯狂了
and it does.
但它确实如此
They’ve just announced they’ve renamed streets in Mar Del Plata
他们刚刚宣布，他们已经以Leo Messi和Scaloni的名字重新命名了Mar Del Plata的街道
after Leo Messi and Scaloni.
以Leo Messi和Scaloni的名字
You talk about what this means...
你说说这意味着什么
They haven’t even won it yet.
他们还没有赢呢
Meanwhile I finally came across the reason
同时，我终于找到了原因
we’d come across so many Bangladeshi flags.
我们遇到了这么多孟加拉国国旗
Bangladesh has been rooting for Argentina since 1986.
我们遇到了这么多孟加拉国国旗 自1986年以来，孟加拉国一直支持阿根廷
Ever since Maradona scored that goal against the English,
自从Maradona攻入对阵英格兰的那粒球以来
the Hand of God.
上帝之手
From that day, the people of Bangladesh
从那天起，孟加拉国人民一直支持阿根廷
which for many years was an English colony.
孟加拉国多年来一直是英国的殖民地
beat a nation as powerful as England,
当他们看到像阿根廷这样的国家击败像英格兰这样强大的国家时
they fell in love with Argentinian football and Maradona.
他们爱上了阿根廷足球和Maradona
And so due to this connection
因此，由于这种联系
Argentina’s World Cup run to the final
阿根廷队闯入世界杯决赛
was creating scenes in Bangladesh
在孟加拉国制造了一些场景
that even impressed the Argentinians.
甚至给阿根廷人留下了深刻的印象
The craziest thing was the flag.
甚至给阿根廷人留下了深刻的印象 最疯狂的事情是旗帜
A 10 km long flag that covered an entire city.
一面10公里长的旗帜覆盖了整个城市
It cost them like 30,000 dollars.
他们花了大约30,000美元。
The thing was gargantuan, crazy.
这东西巨大无比，太疯狂了
Then there were the match day scenes.
然后是比赛日的场景
Over 100,000 people gathering to encourage our national team.
超过10万人聚集在一起为我们的国家队加油
Big screens, sometimes in the middle of the night.
大屏幕，有时在半夜
They don't sleep; they celebrate until 5 or 6 am.
他们不睡觉，他们庆祝到凌晨5、6点
It's madness, and we fell in love with that.
这简直疯了 我们爱上了这一切
And we want to offer them this humble homage.
我们想为他们献上这个谦逊的致敬
We had reached the eve of the Final.
我们已经到了决赛前夜
Where a noticeable change of mood was in the air
空气中弥漫着明显的情绪变化
as the confidence of the past few days
过去几天的信心
seemed to be enveloped by the thought of a loss.
似乎被失败的想法所笼罩
Exactly, this match for Argentina, due to the passion of the people,
没错，这场比赛对阿根廷来说，由于人民的热情
they just can't lose it.
他们就是不能输
It means too much for them.
这对他们来说意义太重大了
I think it's the most important game Argentina's ever played.
我认为这是阿根廷有史以来最重要的一场比赛
Really?
真的吗- 是的
More so than the '86 final?
比86年的决赛更重要吗
More, because...
更重要，因为
Yes, because the team was so strong with Maradona.
是的，因为当时有Maradona，球队非常强大
With this in mind, I decided to head to the stadium
考虑到这一点，我决定前往球场
of Argentinos Juniors.
Argentinos Juniors的球场
The club where Maradona’s career began
Maradona职业生涯开始的俱乐部
and where I’d been told a shrine to Diego had been set up
我听说自从他去世后，那里就为他设立了一个圣地
And it’s here I met Gaston
在那里我遇到了Gaston
whose words and demeanour
他的言语和举止
embodied the anxiety of the entire country.
体现了整个国家的焦虑
Is this tournament now or never for Argentina?
这次比赛对阿根廷来说是“不成功便成仁”吗？
Of course.
当然是
Yes, because Messi may never play again.
是的，因为Messi可能不会再上场了
On the verge of tears the entire time we spoke
在我们谈话的整个过程中，他都快要哭了
Gaston had come to the shrine to pray
Gaston来到圣地祈祷
to the man who had last won the country a World Cup.
向上一次为国家赢得世界杯的人祈祷
I came here today because of tomorrow's game.
我今天来这里是因为明天的比赛
We believe that he's somehow looking down
我们相信他正在以某种方式俯视着
and guiding our national team.
并引导着我们的国家队
And it wasn’t long before more people arrived to do the same.
不久之后，更多的人也来做同样的事情
Are you here about tomorrow?
你是为了明天来的吗
Obviously!
显然
I'm here asking Diego to let us take the cup tomorrow.
我来这里请求Diego明天让我们捧起奖杯
love being Argentinian. I love my country!
我喜欢做阿根廷人，我爱我的国家
We're here asking God.
我们在这里向上帝祈祷
Our God. Our football God.
我们的上帝，我们的足球上帝
We are asking for everyone,
我们为每个人祈祷
for our country, our people, for everyone.
为了我们的国家，我们的人民，为了每个人
To be champions.
成为冠军
We want people to be happy.
我们希望人们快乐
We Argentinians, we have a saying
我们阿根廷人，我们有一句谚语
“Whatever it takes, we have to win tomorrow.”
“无论如何，我们明天必须赢”
And so after 9 long days.
所以在漫长的9天之后
Containing 2 dramatic matches.
包含两场扣人心弦的比赛
In 2 intense cities.
在两个紧张的城市
With dozens of interviews
进行了数十次采访
from dozens of perspectives.
从几十个角度
As the sun began to set on the eve of the final
当决赛前夕太阳开始落山时
I felt we had a pretty clear perspective
我觉得我们对这次世界杯
of this World Cup in this country.
在这个国家有了一个清晰的认识
But I had still had one particularly important interview to conduct
但我还有一个特别重要的采访要做
with my old friend, Izzy.
和我的老朋友Izzy
Who’d been part of all my previous films in Argentina.
他参与了我之前在阿根廷的所有电影
Where he’d always been his unapologetically Argentine self.
在那里，他总是毫不掩饰地展现他的阿根廷本色
And this time was no different.
这一次也不例外
Eli: You look better than ever, unlike me.
Eli：你看起来比以往任何时候都好，不像我
Izzy: l can't say the same but... Eli: Argentinians huh.
Izzy：我不能这么说，但是…… Eli：阿根廷人啊
Izzy: I wouldn't lie.
Izzy：我不会撒谎
When I’d first interviewed Izzy back in 2017
2017年我第一次采访Izzy时
the mere mention of Maradona had him waxing lyrical.
只要提到Maradona，他就会滔滔不绝
Maradona is different, you know?
Maradona是不同的，你知道吗
It’s him against all odds.
是他对抗一切困难
It’s him playing miracles.
是他创造奇迹
It’s like we’re on the verge of dying.
就像我们濒临死亡
And he resurrects us.
他让我们复活
Like Jesus Christ.
就像耶稣基督
Put it like that.
这么说吧
But, when asked about Messi...
但是，当被问到Messi时
If he’s the best player in the world for Barcelona
如果他是巴塞罗那最好的球员
and never delivers for us.
却从来没有为我们带来任何东西
It’s the same as nothing.
那就等于什么都没有
We’re better not having him.
我们最好没有他
Now half a decade later, with the new Maradonian Messi
如今五年过去了 随着“新马拉多纳式”的梅西
having brought Argentina a Copa America
为阿根廷带来了美洲杯
and another World Cup final.
并再次闯入世界杯决赛
I was curious to hear if Izzy
我很想知道Izzy
and his father Marcos
和他的父亲Marcos
who’d supported the team at 6 World Cups around the world...
这位曾支持球队参加过6届世界杯的人……
Felt any differently the day before Messi could finally deliver
在梅西可能最终实现他们等待了36年的梦想的前一天
what they’d been waiting 36 years for...
他们是否会有不同的感受……
and I got my answer straight away.
我立刻得到了答案
There’s no achievement in reaching the final.
进入决赛没有什么成就
The silver medal doesn’t count for anything.
银牌毫无意义
Now, initially, they tried to claim the criticism
起初，他们试图声称这些批评
wasn’t reflective of themselves.
并不能反映他们自己
I’m not saying it’s right
我不是说这是对的
but unfortunately
但不幸的是
knowing my countrymen, if he doesn’t win tomorrow
了解我的同胞们，如果他明天不赢
things are going to go pretty south for him.
事情对他的影响会非常大
But, whenever the question came up
但是，每当问题出现时
of whether Messi had done enough for Argentina
无论决赛结果如何，Messi是否为阿根廷做得足够多
regardless of the result in the final.
无论决赛结果如何
If he wins, if he wins...
如果他赢了，如果他赢了
- If he loses?
- 如果他输了呢
It’s going to be just ahh remember Messi...
只会是“还记得Messi吗……”
He's a loser', if he loses he's a loser'.
“他是个失败者，如果他输了，他就是个失败者”
Nothing he has done before matters.
他以前所做的一切都不重要了
It's all about tomorrow.
一切都取决于明天
We’re like bad parents.
我们就像糟糕的父母
Deep inside we love him but...
内心深处我们爱他，但是
he needs to win!
他需要赢
He needs to win you know.
他需要赢，你知道的
That’s it.
就是这样
You’re so harsh.
你们太苛刻了
If he wins...
如果他赢了
Will you be equally as appreciative?
你会同样感激吗
Messi’s my idol.
Messi是我的偶像
I will put a flag there that says:
我会在那里放一面旗帜，上面写着
“I’m sorry Messi”
“对不起，Messi”
But!
但是
If he doesn’t win...
如果他没有赢
I can’t say on camera what the flag is going to say.
我不能在镜头前说旗帜上会写什么
And if you thought that was harsh.
如果你觉得这很苛刻
Tomorrow will define the story of Messi.
明天将决定Messi的故事
If he wins tomorrow, he's a hero.
如果他明天赢了，他就是英雄
If he loses...
如果他输了
If tomorrow they win!
如果他们明天赢了
It’s Saint Messi.
就是圣Messi
If he lost!
如果他输了
You’re a fucking failure and go back to Spain!
你就是个该死的失败者，滚回西班牙去
And whilst things got a little too heated.
虽然事情变得有点过于激烈
When we did get back on track...
当我们回到正轨时
It was my turn to rant.
轮到我咆哮了
I disagree.
我不同意
Did you not see the interview with the journalist after the match?
你没看到赛后对记者的采访吗
Where she told him:
她告诉他
I don’t want to ask you a question, I want to tell you something
我不想问你问题，我想告诉你一些事情
We want to thank you
我们想感谢你
for making us dream again.
让我们再次梦想
For making us hope again.
让我们再次充满希望
It doesn’t matter the final result.
最终结果并不重要
Yeah but the dream, could turn into a nightmare if we lose.
是的，但如果我们输了，梦想可能会变成噩梦
No but she said! She specifically said, the result...
不，但她说！她特别说了，结果……
She specifically said the result doesn’t matter.
她特别说了，结果并不重要
And she was speaking on behalf of the whole country?
她是代表整个国家发言的吗
Yeah...
是的
Why?
为什么
Or maybe, she was speaking on behalf of...
或者说，她是代表……
of a generation or two.
一两代人说的
A different generation to you guys.
与你们不同的一代人
A generation who didn’t get to see Maradona’s wonders, but
没有看到Maradona的奇迹的一代人，但是
what Messi’s given them is...
Messi给了他们……
as close as possible to someone who has
尽可能接近一个已经
become a god, a deity,
成为神，成为神灵的人
is another unattainable Argentinian dream.
是另一个遥不可及的阿根廷梦
Maybe, you need to relax that
也许，你需要放松一下
and forget it and let it go...
放下这些 让它过去……
and go, you got to see something beautiful.
去欣赏你们所见证的美好
But this tournament...
但这届比赛
Yes this tournament is different.
是的，这届比赛是不同的
Yes.
是的
He’s shown the fight.
他展现了斗志
He’s argued with refs.
他与裁判争论
He’s argued with players.
他与球员争论
He’s remonstrated against coaches.
他抗议教练
He’s done it all!
他做了所有的事
Yeah, but he has one last thing to do.
是的，但他还有一件事要做
To win.
赢
Tomorrow.
明天
Alright, well, here we go.
好吧，我们开始吧
The sun rises on arguably Argentina’s most important,
太阳升起 这可能是阿根廷最重要
most significant day...
最具意义的一天……
this century maybe?
也许是本世纪？
I’m not just talking about in a sporting context.
我不仅仅是在体育方面谈论
I’m talking about in general.
我是一般来说的
I know Argentina has gone through a lot...
我知道阿根廷经历了很多
A lot lately.
最近很多
I’ve heard a lot in the past, but...
我过去听过很多，但是
You know, everyone you speak to
你知道，你与每个人交谈
whether they’re young, old...
无论他们是年轻的，年老的
rich, poor...
富有的，贫穷的
Everyone says the same thing.
每个人都这么说
They’ve never felt such a dramatic shift
他们从未感受到如此剧烈的变化
in the mood of society.
在社会情绪方面
And it’s all been leading up to this!
而这一切都指向了今天！
It’s funny, you know I always get emotionally caught up in
这很有趣，你知道我总是被我正在讲述的故事所感动
whichever story I’m telling.
无论它在世界的哪个角落
But I don’t think I’ve ever been as emotionally involved
但我不认为我曾经像在这里这样投入过感情
as I have, here.
像我在这里一样
This time.
这一次
I haven’t shaved because of Cabalas.
因为Cabalas，我没有刮胡子
I haven’t slept because of nerves.
因为紧张，我没有睡觉
The other day interviewing Maia...
前几天采访Maia时
I started crying two questions into her answers and
在她回答的第二个问题时，我就开始哭了，而且
whilst yes her words were poetic, beautiful,
虽然，是的，她的话语很诗意，很美
there was something deeper you know?
但你知道，还有什么更深层次的东西吗
I’ve really started to realise what was at stake here.
我真的开始意识到这里的利害关系
I’ve really started to realise how this might be...
我真的开始意识到这可能是
not just the football story of the year...
不仅仅是年度足球故事
This might be the footballing story of the decade.
这可能是十年来的足球故事
That’s extreme but...
这有点极端，但是
You gotta look at it like this:
你得这样看
I didn’t grow up with this game.
我并不是从小就看足球的
I found it in my teens when I started seeing how
我在十几岁的时候发现了它，当我开始看到它是如何
it entrenched itself
它是如何融入一个人的灵魂的
into a person’s soul.
融入一个人的灵魂
Into a community.
融入一个社区
Into a country like no other sport...
融入一个国家，就像其他任何运动一样
Like, no other anything...
就像，其他任何东西一样
could.
都无法比拟的
And I feel like Argentinians
我觉得阿根廷人
whether its because of their
无论是因为他们的
extroverted ways,
外向的性格
because of their obsessive personality.
还是他们痴迷的个性
Because of their...
又或者是他们……
innate desire to
与生俱来的渴望
want to realise glorious, unattainable
去实现那些辉煌却遥不可及
realistically unachievable dreams...
现实中无法实现的梦想
They may be, more than Brazil,
他们可能比巴西
maybe even more than England...
甚至比英格兰……
the most passionate football nation.
都更加热爱足球
At least when it comes to this tournament
至少在谈到这场比赛时
and it comes to their national team
谈到他们的国家队时
and their number tens.
以及他们的10号球员
You know in his book about football and his time spent here
你知道，在他关于足球和他在那里度过的时光的书中
Jonathan Wilson said that:
Jonathan Wilson说过
He doesn’t believe that there’s a country on earth
他不相信地球上还有哪个国家
that romanticizes or intellectualises the game
像阿根廷人那样将比赛浪漫化或理智化
like the Argentinians do.
像阿根廷人那样
And he’s right, it’s true.
他是对的，这是真的
But, for me I think it’s more than that.
但是，对我来说，我认为这还不止于此
It’s the way they
是他们
use football to express themselves.
用足球来表达自己的方式
Through song,
通过歌曲
through hand gestures
通过手势
to the way they bounce.
以及他们跳跃的方式
It’s the way they incorporate it
是他们融入的方式
into their social and political movements.
融入他们的社会和政治运动
It’s the way they...
是他们
cling on to football to give them...
紧紧抓住足球给他们
hope.
希望
When hope seems...
当希望似乎
So far away here.
如此遥远
And so with all of that in mind...
因此，考虑到所有这些
I just can’t help thinking
我不禁想到
how does Argentina...
阿根廷如何
At least in my opinion, the most,
至少在我看来
football and World Cup obsessed nation on earth
世界上最痴迷于足球和世界杯的国家
deal with this?
将如何应对这一切？
And so as kick off approached
因此，随着开球时间的临近
and the streets of Buenos Aires emptied.
布宜诺斯艾利斯的街道空无一人
Once again our crew split up
我们的工作人员再次分头行动
to try and document the fixture
试图记录这场比赛
amongst a variety of different people, places and perspectives.
在不同的人群、地点和视角中
One camera headed to the city fan zone
一台摄像机前往城市球迷区
already at capacity hours before kick off.
那里在比赛开始前几小时就已经爆满
One camera headed to a family home
另一台摄像机前往
that of Izzy and his father Marcos.
Izzy和他父亲Marcos的家
We found one Argentinian cameraman
我们找到了一位阿根廷摄影师
willing to film for half of the match with Gaston.
愿意和Gaston一起拍摄半场比赛
The supporter I’d met at the Maradona shrine.
我在马拉多纳圣地遇到的那位球迷
And as for me, and my cameraman Igal
至于我和我的摄影师Igal
we were determined to capture the essence
我们决心捕捉
of the streets of Buenos Aires
布宜诺斯艾利斯街头的精髓
on the day of Argentina’s only ever
在阿根廷有史以来唯一一次
World Cup final in their Summer.
在夏季举行的世界杯决赛当天
And so after a long time searching, I found Ronaldo.
经过长时间的寻找，我找到了Ronaldo
The only cab driver willing to work during the match
唯一一个愿意在比赛期间工作的出租车司机
and that was only because he was Venezuelan,
而这仅仅因为他是委内瑞拉人
and we’d offered him nearly a months salary.
我们给了他将近一个月的工资
And so together we roamed the deserted streets of the capital
于是我们一起漫步在首都空旷的街道上
visiting the small businesses that couldn’t afford to shut
探访那些无法关门的小企业
even though the government announced it was a public holiday.
尽管政府宣布这一天是公共假期
From bakeries
从面包店
to butchers.
到肉店
From cafes.
从咖啡馆
To kiosks.
到小卖部
And though our strategy didn’t get off to the best start
虽然我们的策略并没有取得最好的开始
thanks to a very Argentinian reason...
由于一个非常阿根廷的原因
That’s amazing!
太棒了
So, we wanted to watch it with the people
所以，我们想和大家一起看
but they don’t want to watch it with me!
但他们不想和我一起看
Because I might be Cabalas.
因为我可能带来坏运气
Luckily, we found a grocery store, willing to accommodate us
幸运的是，我们找到了一家杂货店，愿意接纳我们
just in time for kick off.
正好赶上开球
I mean we’re 90 minutes away man.
我的意思是，我们还有90分钟
I can’t believe I’m saying that.
我不敢相信我说了这句话
We’re 90 minutes away.
我们还有90分钟
90 minutes away from...
距离比赛只有90分钟了……
I mean I’ve heard stories my whole life
我的意思是，我这辈子都听过这样的故事
of my parents talking about ‘78, Kempes.
我的父母谈论78年，Kempes
‘86, Maradona.
86年，Maradona
And I’ve been fed those stories constantly whilst never quite...
我一直被灌输这些故事，却从来没有
watching it for myself.
亲眼看过
And now, I finally, finally have that chance.
现在，我终于，终于有机会了
We’re only one game away.
我们只有一场比赛了
One game away from finally creating my own stories
距离最终创造我自己的故事只有一场比赛了
of Argentina winning the World Cup.
关于阿根廷赢得世界杯的故事
Do you understand that?
你明白吗
And so we were off.
于是我们出发了
The 2022 FIFA World Cup Final had begun.
2022年FIFA世界杯决赛开始了
And the entire nation was strapped in
整个国家都系好了安全带
for one final ride on the emotional rollercoaster that is
在这场情感过山车上进行最后一次旅程
supporting this nation at this tournament.
支持这支国家队在这次赛事中的表现
And whilst France may have been the best team in the world
虽然法国可能是世界上最好的球队
it was Argentina who began with all the chances.
但阿根廷一开始就拥有所有机会
The only problem being...
唯一的问题是
they weren’t taking any of them.
他们没有抓住任何一个
Meanwhile I was back on the road looking
同时，我回到了路上，寻找
to find other people and places to watch
其他人和地方观看比赛
to get as broad a perspective as possible on such a unique day.
以便在这样一个独特的日子里获得尽可能广泛的视角
Yet no matter the person.
然而，无论这个人是谁
No matter the place.
无论在什么地方
It was the same talking point it had been all week.
这都是整个星期以来一直在谈论的话题
Messi.
Messi
The entire country is on Messi's shoulders right now.
现在整个国家都压在Messi的肩上
Even politicians aren't under as much pressure as Messi.
即使是政治家也没有Messi那么大的压力
This is the key moment for Messi to consecrate himself,
这是Messi加冕的关键时刻
because he's close to the end of his career,
因为他即将结束他的职业生涯
to become the best player in the world.
成为世界上最好的球员
But Messi needs the World Cup.
但Messi需要世界杯
Argentina's story with Messi depends on tomorrow's game.
阿根廷与Messi的故事取决于明天的比赛
If he wins, he'll be put up there on a throne
如果他赢了，他将被供奉在王座上
If he loses, he'll be placed under ground.
如果他输了，他就会被埋在地下
He has to win tomorrow.
他明天必须赢
Journalists will destroy him if they don't win tomorrow.
如果他们明天不赢，记者们会毁了他
Our society as well.
我们的社会也是
Because, so far, he hasn't been able to compete with Maradona.
因为，到目前为止，他还无法与Maradona竞争
What would he have to do to reach Maradona’s level?
他要怎么做才能达到Maradona的水平
To be in the same conversation?
进行同样的讨论
At least win the World Cup.
至少赢得世界杯
He’s 90 minutes away.
他还有90分钟
And be part of it.
并成为其中的一员
Not like Ronaldo in the Euro 2016.
不能像2016年欧洲杯上的Ronaldo
Score the goal.
要进球
Penalty Argentina.
阿根廷点球
21 minutes in.
21分钟
This is actually happening.
这真的发生了
Who takes the penalty?
谁来罚点球
Even our cab driver, Ronaldo.
即使是我们的出租车司机，Ronaldo
Get in here.
进来吧
Messi is a penalty kick away
梅西距离连马拉多纳都未能做到的事情只差一个点球
Scoring in a final.
在决赛中进球
Show us why you’re the best in the world.
向我们展示你为什么是世界上最好的
Let’s go outside.
我们出去吧
Listen.
听着
They say when you go to Argentina...
他们说，当你去阿根廷的时候
Look at that!
看看那个
Argentina are in front.
阿根廷领先了
Messi has scored in a World Cup final.
Messi在世界杯决赛中进球了
Look what it means.
看看这意味着什么
He’s actually done it.
他真的做到了
People are on the street.
人们在街上
It’s actually f**king happening!
这真的他*的发生了！
Now, whether it was the sunstroke or the orchestra of balcony roars.
现在，无论是中暑还是阳台上震耳欲聋的欢呼声
It’s fair to say I’d lost my head
公平地说，我已经失去了理智
and was completely swept up in the occasion
完全沉浸在这种场合中
high fiving traffic and hugging strangers on the street
与路过的车辆击掌 与街上的陌生人拥抱
but eventually I did remember there was still the vast majority
但最终我还是意识到
of the game still to be played.
比赛还有很长时间
And so we entered our fifth location of the day
于是我们进入了当天的第五个地点
where we had just enough time for a quick dance
在那里我们有足够的时间快速跳个舞
and a quick drink to calm down
快速喝一杯冷静一下
before Argentina were on the attack once again.
在阿根廷再次进攻之前
And whilst it’s evident I lost my head once again
虽然很明显我又一次失去了理智
in all fairness...
平心而论
So had everyone else...
其他人也一样
As children.
孩子们
Teenagers.
青少年
And even grown adults
甚至成年人
all seemed overcome with all kinds of emotions.
似乎都被各种各样的情绪所淹没
As one by one it seemed to dawn on everyone
一个接一个地 大家似乎都意识到
that Argentina might really be winning a World Cup again.
阿根廷可能真的要再次赢得世界杯了
To the streets! To the streets!
上街去！上街去！
And as incredible as it was being amongst the chaos indoors
虽然置身于室内的混乱之中令人难以置信
I was desperate once again to experience that roar of the streets
但我再次渴望体验街头上的欢呼声
that only a Buenos Aires World Cup match day can provide.
只有在布宜诺斯艾利斯世界杯比赛日才能体验到的
Where are you going?
你要去哪里
The Obelisco!
方尖碑
The Obelisco right now?!?
现在就去方尖碑？
But it isn't over yet?
但比赛还没有结束
They’re already going to the Obelisk!
他们已经要去方尖碑了
Never before had a halftime felt as needed for the players
从未有过一次中场休息像这次一样  球员们需要它
as it did the supporters,
对于球迷来说也是如此
myself included.
包括我自己
As already everyone seemed to be already emotionally exhausted.
因为每个人似乎都已经精疲力尽了
This country runs on football, on passion, the things we love.
因为每个人似乎都已经精疲力尽了 这个国家依靠足球、激情和我们热爱的东西运转
Football is one of the things we most love.
足球是我们最热爱的东西之一
The team's strength and the strength of 45 million Argentinians.
球队的力量和4500万阿根廷人的力量
Argentinians who can't eat and can't sleep.
那些吃不下睡不着的阿根廷人
Can't think of anything else.
想不出其他任何事情
It's the last one we want. The last one we need.
这是我们想要的最后一个，也是我们需要的最后一个
And it's the last one he (Messi) deserves.
这也是他（Messi）应得的最后一个
Because not only does he deserve it.
因为他不仅应该得到它
We all deserve it,
我们都值得
because of all we've resisted, and all we've endured.
因为我们所抵抗的一切，以及我们所忍受的一切
It's all that we ask.
这就是我们所要求的
It's all we ask. All we ask God.
这就是我们向上帝祈求的全部
We don't ask him for anything else.
我们没有向他要求其他任何东西
We may be having a rough time, going hungry...
我们可能正在经历一段艰难的时期，正在挨饿
but this is all we ask for.
但这就是我们所要求的全部
Not a thing more.
仅此而已
For us, for just one more World Cup, to be on top again...
对我们来说 再赢得一次世界杯 再次站在巅峰……
seeing Messi raise the World Cup...
看到Messi举起世界杯
could change this country.
可以改变这个国家
And so the Second Half began
下半场开始了
with the country in the best mood
全国人民的心情都处于我所见过的最佳状态
I had ever seen it.
我所见过的最佳状态
As the final forty five minutes
随着最后的45分钟
were being counted down with an energy and an enthusiasm
以一种能量和热情倒计时
that could only be described as a collective shedding
整个国家集体释放了
of the 36 years worth of hurt and heartbreak
这个国家36年来在这项赛事中所承受的伤痛和心碎
And so as we slowly made our way deeper into the city.
因此，随着我们慢慢深入城市
I started noticing that the roads and footpaths were a lot busier
我开始注意到，道路和人行道比上半场繁忙得多
So naturally I had to find out more.
所以，自然而然地，我必须了解更多
For some it was just another case of Argentine superstition.
对一些人来说，这只是阿根廷迷信的又一个例子
Why aren't you viewing the game in your house?
你为什么不在家看比赛
It's cábala, my brother.
这是cábala，我的兄弟
This is win or win.
这是赢或赢
In whatever way, but we win.
无论如何，我们都会赢
I was watching the game (at home)
我在（家里）看比赛
and I went out to buy candles...
然后我出去买蜡烛
I'm going to drive around. I go in circles.
我要开车四处转转 我转圈
I'm going to shout and I'm going to honk my horn.
我要大喊大叫，我还要按喇叭
Candles... to burn.
蜡烛……燃烧
To burn for good energy.
燃烧以带来好能量
Igal: Have you watched the whole match in your car?
Igal：你是在车里看完整场比赛的吗
- Yes!
-是的！
And then I saw this (Screen) and i decided to stay
然后我看到了这个（屏幕），我决定留下来
It's my way.
这是我的方式 我的疯狂
And I get too nervous watching.
而且我看比赛会太紧张
Because of the cábalas?
因为迷信吗？
Yeah, cábalas.
是的 迷信
For cábalas
为了迷信
For others, it was just a case sheer optimism.
对其他人来说，这只是纯粹的乐观主义
Igal: Why are you in your car? Not watching the game?
对其他人来说，这只是纯粹的乐观主义 Igal：你为什么在你的车里？不看比赛吗
Because we're heading to the Obelisco, where everyone is.
因为我们正前往方尖碑，那里是每个人都在的地方
The fans! The people!
球迷们！人们！
Obelisco! Right now?
方尖碑！现在吗？
Igal: But it's not over!
Igal：但比赛还没有结束！
Not yet!
还没有！
Regardless!
不管怎样！
Come on! The third goal is coming!
加油！第三个进球就要来了！
This is actually insane.
这真是太疯狂了
There is so many more cars on the street than I thought.
街上的车比我想象的要多得多
You know and it turns out everyone is going to the Obelisco early.
你知道吗，结果每个人都提前去了方尖碑
There’s still half an hour left.
还有半个小时
Yeah, yeah, get excited.
是啊，是啊，兴奋起来
You’re half an hour away from ending this 36 year drought.
你离结束这36年的干旱只有半小时了
But you’re still Argentina.
但你仍然是阿根廷
You can still suffer!
你仍然会受苦！
It was only a few games ago...
就在几场比赛前
That Dutch match.
那场荷兰队的比赛
Let’s not get too cocky.
我们不要太得意忘形
15 minutes to get to the '90.
还有15分钟就到90分钟了
And so we were off to our next location.
于是我们去了下一个地点
Where that reserved anticipation I was hoping for
在那里 我所期待的克制和期待
was nowhere to be seen.
无处可见
And it was the same in the fan zone
球迷区也是一样
where with just over ten minutes to go
在只剩下10多分钟的时候
the finish line was in sight and being celebrated accordingly.
终点线已经在望 大家开始庆祝
In fact the only corner of the country
事实上 整个国家唯一
that didn’t seem swept up in a similar euphoria
没有被类似的兴奋所席卷的角落
was Izzy’s house.
是Izzy的家
And whether that was down to their experience or their cynicism
无论是因为他们的经验还是他们的怀疑态度
turns out they were right to be cautious.
事实证明，他们谨慎是对的
Fu**ing clear it!
该死的，解围！
I told you!
我告诉过你！
A penalty?
点球？
Yeah for them.
是的，是他们的
For... them?
他们…的？
And whilst I couldn’t get a clear sight at the screen
虽然我看不清屏幕
to see what was going on...
不知道发生了什么
I think it’s a penalty to France.
我想这是一个给法国的点球
They're singing (for goalkeeper) Dibu...
他们在为（门将）Dibu唱歌…
Mbappé was already lining up the spot kick.
Mbappé已经站在点球点了
Mbappé scores.
Mbappé得分
France score. 2-1
法国队进球了 2-1
I told you, I told you.
我告诉过你，我告诉过你
These guys...
这些人……
Only know how to suffer.
只知道如何受苦
Oh no, now this...
哦，不，现在这……
Now begins the stress.
现在开始有压力了
But, before the anxiety could even kick in.
但是，在焦虑开始之前
Before the prayers could even be answered.
在祈祷得到回应之前
Before the worst case scenario could even be imagined.
在最坏的情况发生之前
Izzy: I cān't live football like this!
Izzy：我不能这样活在足球里！
After leading the match
在领先了
for 57 minutes
57分钟后
including a two goal lead
包括两球领先
for 45 minutes.
45分钟
With only ten minutes left
只剩下十分钟了
Argentina had given it all up
阿根廷在97秒内
within the space of 97 seconds.
失去了一切
And so as the hands of happiness in the air
于是 原本高举的双手
were replaced with hands of heartbreak on heads.
被头上心碎的双手所取代
I was now starting to realise
我现在开始意识到
there was actually quite a lot of sense
Izzy的愤世嫉俗实际上很有道理
In Izzy’s cynicism.
在Izzy的愤世嫉俗中
You’re right. (A World Cup Final) is a dream.
你是对的（世界杯决赛）是一个梦想
But a nightmare is a type of dream too you know?
但噩梦也是一种梦想，你知道吗
And losing the World Cup, in the Final.
在决赛中输掉世界杯
It’s a fu**ing nightmare.
这真是个噩梦
It’s getting so close.
越来越近了
So close.
如此接近
I much prefer, like, losing Quarter Finals.
我更喜欢在四分之一决赛中输球
And so as we moved on to our next location.
于是我们搬到了下一个地点
Where the mood was neither warm nor welcoming...
那里的气氛既不热情也不友好
Because we think we could win.
因为我们认为我们能赢
But if that doesn’t happen...
但如果这没有发生
Everything goes away.
一切都将消失
All the love will go away.
所有的爱都将消失
Minute by minute Izzy’s predictions played out...
Izzy的预言一分一秒地应验了
This country and football...
这个国家和足球
What's up man? What's up?
怎么了，伙计？怎么了？
Whoa, whoa, whoa...
哇，哇，哇
We’re not saying that we personally feel like that.
我们不是说我们个人有这种感觉
We’re just saying that knowing our country.
我们只是说，了解我们的国家
And knowing our people.
了解我们的人民
If he doesn’t win tomorrow...
如果他明天不赢
This is what’s going to happen.
就会发生这样的事情
Again he was right...
他又一次说对了
As we began seeing Argentinians threatening
当我们开始看到阿根廷人互相威胁时
and turning on each other.
互相攻击
And so as we moved away for our own safety
因此，为了我们自身的安全，我们离开了
Once again it was Izzy’s words, this time from our chat in 2017
再一次，是Izzy的话，这次是我们2017年的谈话
that rang true.
听起来很真实
I’ll say it in Spanish.
我用西班牙语说
Regardless!
不管怎样
we live our lives between glory and hell
我们的生活在荣耀和地狱之间
And, well, with the glory period long gone with that lead...
随着领先优势的消失，荣耀时期早已过去
We found ourselves stuck in what felt like Argentinian hell.
我们发现自己陷入了阿根廷的地狱
No more so than when the guy from the argument returned.
尤其是当那个吵架的人回来的时候
Because that thing he’s looking down at under his shirt.
因为他衬衫下面藏着的东西
Well you may not be able to see it.
你可能看不到
But I can.
但我能看到
And it’s a gun.
那是一把枪
And as desperate as I was document every angle of this final
尽管我非常渴望从布宜诺斯艾利斯街头的角度
from the perspective of the Buenos Aires streets.
记录这场决赛的每一个细节
Even I didn’t want to stick around to find out what happened next.
即使是我也不想留下来看接下来会发生什么
Eli: Let's go. He has a gun. Drive, drive. He has a gun
Eli：快走 他有枪 开车 开车 他有枪
Why are you guys like this? So black and white?
你们为什么是这样的？如此黑白分明？
Eli: Holy shit. Did you see that?
Eli：天啊 你看到了吗？
Heaven or Hell, it’s like...
天堂或地狱，就像……
Actually that’s the best analogy!
事实上，这是最好的比喻！
That’s Maradona! Heaven or Hell.
这就是Maradona！天堂或地狱
There’s no middle ground.
没有中间地带
There’s no shades of grey.
没有灰色地带
Black or white.
黑色或白色
Out of nowhere, 2-0 up and then...
不知不觉中，2-0领先，然后……
We’re pulling guns on each other.
我们互相拔枪相向
This beautiful...
这美丽的……
Chaotic...
混乱的
Glorious, but
光荣的，但是
flawed country man.
充满缺陷的国家 兄弟
Their football. The experiences this tournament (creates)
他们的足球 这次世界杯（带来的）经历
Couldn’t embody this country more.
再完美不过地体现了这个国家
To go from such glorious highs...
从如此辉煌的高峰……
to lows.
到低谷
But if we thought we had seen the lowest point,
但如果我们认为我们已经看到了最低点
well, we were sorely mistaken
那么，我们大错特错了
as only a few minutes later
几分钟后
and only a few blocks up the exact same street
就在同一条街的几个街区外
we found out just how chaotic Argentina can get on such a day.
我们发现了在这样的一天里，阿根廷会有多么混乱
Something’s happening.
出事了
Just like those at the fan zone.
就像球迷区的人们一样
Just like those at Izzy’s house.
就像Izzy家的人们一样
The emotional rollercoaster of this final had pushed me to the edge.
这场决赛的情绪过山车把我推到了崩溃的边缘
IGAL: Straight?
IGAL：直走？
Ah, si, I don’t know anymore.
啊，是的，我不知道了
I don’t know where we’re going anymore.
我不知道我们要去哪里了
I don’t know what’s going on anymore.
我不知道发生了什么事
Just drive.
开车吧
Drive.
开车
F*ck Me
我靠
It’s 2-2 still?
还是2-2？
Why did everyone think it was a penalty?
为什么每个人都认为是点球？
The guy in the bar was crying?
酒吧里的人哭了？
And so as full time was called
于是 当全场比赛结束时
with the footpaths of Buenos Aires filled with despondent bodies
布宜诺斯艾利斯的人行道上挤满了沮丧的人
and the roads filled with SWAT teams preparing for the worst.
道路上挤满了准备迎接最坏情况的特警队
I tried my best to sum it all up.
我尽力总结这一切
Ah, how poetic.
啊，多么诗意
The exact same spot where I stopped 30 minutes ago and said:
就在30分钟前我停下来的同一个地方，我说过
Let’s not get too excited at 2-0.
2-0的时候不要太兴奋
Since then it has gone to 2-2.
从那以后，比分变成了2-2
But in that time we’ve seen fights.
但在这段时间里，我们看到了打架
I’ve seen a gun. I’ve seen a man pull a gun.
我看到了一把枪 我看到一个人拔出了枪
And we’ve heard what we think are gunshots.
我们听到了我们认为是枪声的声音
I said it up on the rooftop this morning...
我今天早上在屋顶上说过……
I just can’t help thinking with...
我不禁想到……
what it’s 5:30 now?
现在几点了？5:30？
Less than 7 hours to go...
还有不到7个小时……
Am I ready for this?
我准备好了吗
Are we ready for this?
我们准备好了吗
Is this country ready for this?
这个国家准备好了吗
When you consider how already emotional
考虑到他们已经如此情绪化
they are about everything.
对所有事情
When you consider everything that’s gone in the last two weeks.
当你考虑到过去两周发生的一切
It’s like the entire city...
就像整个城市……
It’s spirit has been sucked through the drains.
它的精神已经被吸干了
People are crying on every corner.
每个角落都有人在哭泣
People aren’t watching the match.
人们没有在看比赛
People are fighting.
人们在打架
And so the pain and the suffering and the...
所以痛苦、苦难和……
the wait goes on.
等待还在继续
And the emotions continue...
情绪还在继续……
Extra time had came with a palpable shift in mood.
加时赛开始时 气氛明显发生了变化
Where the anger at the giving up such a lead so quickly
原本因为迅速失去领先优势而产生的愤怒
had been replaced with a sadness
已经被悲伤所取代
at just how precarious the situation was.
因为局势变得如此脆弱
If Messi doesn't bring home this Cup
如果Messi不把奖杯带回家
it's going to be Argentina's saddest Christmas
这将是阿根廷最悲伤的圣诞节
Of course. Remember World Cups are usually in June and July.
当然。记住世界杯通常在六月和七月举行
But now, with the change of date...
但现在，随着日期的改变……
[losingl would make it the saddest Christmas in Argentinian history.
（输球）将使它成为阿根廷历史上最悲伤的圣诞节
But it wasn’t for a lack of trying
但这并不是因为缺乏尝试
as from the moment extra time kicked off
从加时赛开始的那一刻起
Argentina dominated.
阿根廷占据了主导地位
With chance.
有机会
After chance.
一次又一次的机会
But ultimately nothing to show for it.
但最终却没有什么收获
So as the first half of extra time came to an end,
所以，随着加时赛上半场的结束
despite the encouraging signs.
尽管有令人鼓舞的迹象
There was a feeling that with their best squad in decades
但有一种感觉是 凭借他们几十年来最好的阵容
and arguably their best ever player,
以及可以说是他们有史以来最好的球员
Argentina had 15 minutes to finish the job
阿根廷还有15分钟来完成比赛
before it came down to the lottery of penalties.
否则将进入点球大战的赌局
For the final 15 minutes we were on the move again
在最后的15分钟里，我们再次出发了
and I only had once place in mind.
我只想到了一个地方
Tucuman street, where all the chaos had occurred.
图库曼街，所有混乱都发生在那里
Can we go past Tucuman (street) and just see?
我们能经过图库曼街看看吗
Yeah, I just want to go down Tucuman.
是的，我只想沿着图库曼街走下去
Yeah, if there’s a cop car there now.
是的，如果现在那里有警车的话
Let’s go past Tucuman.
我们经过图库曼街吧
And so as we headed back to Tucuman
所以当我们回到图库曼的时候
once again all I could think about
我能想到的只有
was Izzy.
是Izzy
And how despite being so outspoken, he’d got so much right.
以及尽管他如此直言不讳，但他却说对了这么多
He’d doubted Argentina’s chances.
他怀疑阿根廷的机会
He’d predicted the ensuing nightmare.
他预言了随之而来的噩梦
And somehow, he’d even predicted how
不知何故，他甚至预言了
the actual final would play out.
真正的决赛将如何进行
You’re two goals up in the final of a World Cup.
你在世界杯决赛中领先两球
It’s there.
就在那里
And they tie it! 2-2!
他们扳平了！2-2！
This is Tucuman. It’s right here. It’s right here.
这就是图库曼街 就在这里 就在这里
Maradona...
Maradona……
He would grab the ball...tuk
他会抓住球……
and you can go and score.
然后你可以去得分
Can we keep the camera down a bit lower.
能让镜头低一点吗
You knew in your head he would save you.
你知道他会救你的
And Messi is like...
Messi就像……
I don’t know.
我不知道
The guy pulled the gun right there.
那家伙就在那里拔出了枪
IGAL: Yeah
IGAL：是的
You still believe that to this day?
你至今仍然相信吗
Yes to this day.
是的，直到今天
And then in the 108th minute
然后在第108分钟
As we sat outside Tucuman pondering what to do next...
当我们坐在图库曼外面思考下一步该做什么时……
He lacks epicness, Messi.
他缺乏史诗般的能力，Messi
Izzy was finally proven wrong.
Izzy终于被证明是错的 他缺乏史诗性，Messi
You’re kidding me!
你在开玩笑吧！
Argentina were back in the lead of a World Cup Final.
阿根廷在世界杯决赛中再次领先
And if that wasn’t epic enough...
如果这还不够史诗的话……
And if you thought Izzy’s remorse was a drastic change of heart
如果你认为Izzy的悔恨是心态的剧烈转变
what was happening where we were, was on a whole other level.
我们所在的地方发生的事情，完全是另一个层次
That’s the man who pulled out the gun.
就是那个拔枪的人
Only thirty minutes ago I saw that man pull out a gun.
就在30分钟前，我看到那个人拔出了一把枪
And so once again the pendulum swung from Argentine hell
于是 钟摆再次从阿根廷的地狱
to a very Argentine glory.
摆向了阿根廷的荣耀
I can’t stress this enough.
我再怎么强调也不为过
You talk about the glorious highs and the epic lows.
你谈论着辉煌的高潮和史诗般的低谷
Argentina...
阿根廷……
That man pulled out a gun on someone in that exact spot...
那个人就在那个地方拔枪指着某人……
All sense of control.
所有的控制感
All sense of calm.
所有的平静感
All sense of, well...
所有感觉，好吧……
sense.
感觉
Had vanished in the whirlwind of chaos this match had created.
在这场比赛中 一切都在混乱中消失了
Where even the most stubborn were now questioning everything...
即使是最顽固的人现在也在质疑一切……
And so with the lead and the glory back in Argentina’s hands
于是 随着领先优势和荣耀再次回到阿根廷手中
with only minutes to go,
距离比赛结束只有几分钟
we got back in the taxi and headed towards the Obelisk
我们回到了出租车上，向方尖碑驶去
where in only a matter of moments
在那里，只需片刻
we knew the entire country would be descending...
我们知道整个国家都会涌向那里……
But, we should have known better...
但是，我们应该更清楚……
IGAL: Penalty for France.
IGAL：法国队获得点球
You’re kidding me.
你在开玩笑吧
No, you’re kidding me.
不，你在开玩笑吧
Just like everyone else around the country
就像全国各地的其他人一样
I had just given up trying to make sense
我已经放弃了试图理解
of what was going on.
发生了什么
How can I...
我怎么能……
This country is...
这个国家是……
Nah...
不……
Nah...I’m done.
不……我受够了
When was the penalty?
点球是什么时候
How can I??
我怎么能？
How can I articulate...
我怎么能表达清楚……
What this is at this point?
这是什么情况？
What’s going on...
发生了什么事……
And so as we approached one of the main streets off the Obelisk
所以当我们靠近方尖碑附近的一条主要街道时
we came across hundreds of others just like us
我们遇到了数百个像我们一样的人
who’d headed to the place of celebration a little too early
他们过早地前往庆祝地点
and were now desperately trying to flock to nearby TV’s
现在正拼命地涌向附近的电视
to try and get a view of the dying minutes of the game.
试图看到比赛最后几分钟的画面
And so, for the final time...
于是 最后一次……
we got out at another location.
我们到了另一个地方
Where the mood was neither glorious nor hellish
那里的气氛既不是辉煌的 也不是地狱般的
but instead a kind of Argentinian pergutory.
而是一种阿根廷式的炼狱
And so as I stood amongst this scene of sadness
所以当我站在这悲伤的景象中
trying to guess what was going on in the final moments of the game
试图猜测在比赛的最后时刻发生了什么
as I had no chance of getting near a TV screen.
因为我没有机会靠近电视屏幕
I came across Laura
我遇到了Laura
who, pacing up and down the street with tears in her eyes
她泪流满面地在街上踱来踱去
seemed particularly affected.
似乎受到了特别的影响
But suffer they did, as those final minutes of extra time
但他们确实很痛苦，因为加时赛的最后几分钟
belonged to a resurgent France side
属于复苏的法国队
aiming to score a fourth
他们试图打进第四球
and put the final dagger into Argentina
在进入点球大战之前
before we could even reach penalties.
给阿根廷最后一击
In all honesty...
老实说……
if Diego is on our side, l just don't know
如果Diego站在我们这边，我不知道
And so with Argentina holding on for dear life.
所以，阿根廷为了生存而坚持
It's the only joy we can look forward to in this country.
这是我们在这个国家唯一可以期待的快乐
It's the only joy.
这是唯一的快乐
After 3 and half decades plus 120 minutes of excruciating waiting
经过30多年零120分钟的煎熬等待
it looked like their World Cup dream, or nightmare
看起来他们的世界杯之梦，或者说是噩梦
would be decided in football’s most excruciating way.
将以足球最残酷的方式决定
Penalties?
点球大战？
We’re going to penalties.
我们要进入点球大战了
Diego if you’re up there...
Diego，如果你在那里……
Please, there’s five kicks.
拜托，有五次罚球
And so this was it.
就是这样了
After 36 and a half years.
36年半之后
Or 462 months.
或者462个月
Or 13, 321 days.
或者13321天
Somehow this country’s ultimate desire.
不知何故，这个国家的终极愿望
Ultimate obsession.
终极痴迷
Ultimate dream.
终极梦想
Was now at the mercy of a series of kicks from the 12 yard spot.
现在只能听天由命地进行一系列12码罚球
If we go to penalties, but if we go to penalties?
如果我们进入点球大战，但如果我们进入点球大战？
That would be too much tension
那将会太紧张了
Some people don't even watch. They go
有些人甚至不看比赛 他们走了
Nobody would want to watch such a game
没有人会想看这样的比赛
Does Messi take the first kick? Or the fifth kick?
梅西是第一个踢点球 还是第五个？
No, Messi needs to take the first kick
不 梅西必须第一个踢
- The best always shoots first!-Shoots first, yes
- 最好的球员总是第一个踢！- 第一个踢 是的
One round in and the shootout was already taking it’s toll
一轮过后，点球大战已经开始产生影响了
No more so, than on Laura...
尤其是对Laura……
Argentina, up until now, has always given us a bitter sweet taste
到目前为止，阿根廷总是给我们一种苦乐参半的滋味
Because we've made so many finals, but had so little success
因为我们进了很多次决赛，但成功却很少
Because if you play bad and you lose, that's okay.
因为如果你踢得不好输了，没关系
But if you play well and don't win...
但如果你踢得好却没有赢……
whilst having the best player in the world who takes you to finals
同时拥有世界上最好的球员，他带你进入决赛
more than anything, it's a sadness
最重要的是，这是一种悲伤
Because, football deserves it.
因为，足球值得拥有
So the fact that he made it to the final in his last World Cup
所以 他在最后一届世界杯中打进决赛
it's the right call by destiny.
这是命运的安排
That life gives you bad things, but if you hang on, in good faith,
生活会给你带来不好的事情，但如果你真诚地坚持下去
it will come good.
一切都会好起来的
So l think that's what awictory against France would be.
所以我认为这就是战胜法国的意义
It's a true punch that can give us good things
在经历了如此多的失望之后，这是一次真正的冲击，可以给我们带来美好的事物
after so much disappointment.
在经历了如此多的失望之后
It's true what my nephew says...
我侄子说的没错……
I think that destiny cannot be wrong
我认为命运不会出错
And destiny is set up in a way
命运是以某种方式注定的
that no matter what, the winner of this match will be..Argentina
无论如何，这场比赛的胜者都将是……阿根廷
The second round of penalties had brought a whole new mood.
第二轮点球带来了全新的气氛
But it was the next round...
但接下来的第三轮……
that really saw things change.
真正让局势发生了变化
Saved!
扑救！
Penalty saved!
点球扑救！
And so with a 3-1 lead going into the fourth round of kicks
所以，以3-1的领先优势进入第四轮点球
Argentina just needed to save France’s next penalty
阿根廷只需要扑出法国队的下一个点球
to win the game, and the tournament.
就能赢得比赛，赢得冠军
And the realisation was hitting harder than ever...
这种感觉比以往任何时候都更加强烈……
And whilst France converted their fourth to stay alive
尽管法国队打进了第四球 继续存活
Argentina would still win the World Cup by scoring their next.
但阿根廷只要罚进下一个点球就能赢得世界杯
l'm a Boca fan...
我是Boca球迷……
but Argentina winning the World Cup is the ultimate.
但阿根廷赢得世界杯才是终极目标
I would trade anything for it.
我愿意为此付出一切
What l want most of all is for Argentina to win this World Cup
我最希望的是阿根廷能赢得这届世界杯
for them (the young). For those who haven't seen it.
为了他们（年轻人） 为了那些还没有看过的人
You cannot describe what it's like when
你无法描述
Argentina win the World Cup
阿根廷赢得世界杯时的感觉
I get emotional talking about Argentina.
谈到阿根廷，我变得很激动
I carry it in my soul, and l see what they're doing to us.
我把它记在心里，我看到了他们对我们所做的一切
It's all part of the same thing
这都是同一件事的一部分
I can see that the kids that are studying, working, trying hard...
我可以看到那些正在学习、工作、努力的孩子们……
have no future here and they leave
在这里没有未来，他们离开了
And that kills me.
这让我很难过
I'm bringing several topics to the table, but...
我提出了几个话题，但是……
it's the only joy we can aspire to and
这是我们唯一渴望的快乐，而且
that's why l'm praying to God that we can win the World Cup
这就是为什么我向上帝祈祷我们能赢得世界杯
Football.
足球
Not sport, football.
不是体育，是足球
Football, is the greatest thing on earth.
足球，是地球上最伟大的东西
I’m not having it any other way.
我不接受其他任何说法
It’s the most beautiful thing, it’s the most ugly thing.
这是最美丽的东西，也是最丑陋的东西
It’s the most romantic thing and it’s the most heartbreaking thing.
这是最浪漫的事，也是最心碎的事
It is the most, emotional thing...
这是最具情感的事物……
It is the most, Argentinian thing.
这是最阿根廷的东西
And with one more penalty, with one more penalty...
再进一个点球 再进一个点球……
they end the most romantic story...
他们就结束了最浪漫的故事……
Argentina.
阿根廷
Lionel Messi.
Lionel Messi
Are World Champions.
是世界冠军
The most beautiful story.
最美丽的故事
In the most beautiful game.
在最美丽的比赛中
In the most beautiful tournament of all.
在最美丽的赛事中
I think the yearning for success for Argentina
我认为阿根廷对成功的渴望
I think it’s very hard to overestimate
我认为很难高估
just how much they needed to win
他们有多么需要这场胜利
particularly the World Cup.
尤其是世界杯
It’s been really difficult in Argentina.
在阿根廷真的很难
It’s been difficult socially.
社会上很困难
It’s been difficult economically.
经济上很困难
It’s been difficult politically.
政治上很困难
And so this one moment of pride they’ve been desperate for...
所以他们一直渴望的这一刻的骄傲……
to finally get that.
终于得到了
And to do it in what’s almost certainly Messi’s last tournament.
而且是在几乎可以确定是梅西的最后一届赛事中
In his fifth World Cup.
在他的第五届世界杯上
That’s why it means so much...
这就是为什么它意义如此重大……
For Messi and Argentina it was the perfect finale.
对梅西和阿根廷来说 这是完美的结局
It was love.
是爱
It was the romance coming together after all these...
这是经历了所有高潮和低谷后
highs and lows.
浪漫的汇聚
I’m sorry Messi.
对不起，Messi
I ask for your forgiveness.
我请求你的原谅
I killed you for years.
我多年来一直在诋毁你
I’m sorry, I’m sorry!
对不起，对不起！
What we suffered and what we enjoyed in that World Cup.
我们在那届世界杯上所承受的和所享受的
No other memory can take that away.
没有任何其他记忆可以取代它
It’s gonna be special, forever.
这将是特别的，永远的
And the fact that it’s December.
而且这发生在十二月
The fact that it’s not the normal time for the World Cup Final.
这不是世界杯决赛的常规时间
Argentinians experienced it differently.
阿根廷人以不同的方式体验了它
The fact that it was their summer rather than their winter.
这是他们的夏天 而不是冬天
There’s this question that’s been there since the British retreat
自从20世纪初英国从阿根廷撤退以来
from Argentina in the first couple of decades of the 20th century.
一直存在一个问题
Que es Argentinidad? What is it?
什么是阿根廷特有的特性？它是什么？
What is Argentinian-ness?
什么是阿根廷气质？
What is it to be Argentinian?
成为阿根廷人意味着什么？
And what it is now is football.
现在它就是足球
That is the way that Argentina expresses itself on the world stage.
这就是阿根廷在世界舞台上表达自己的方式
And seeing the scenes after the final of...
看到决赛后的景象……
5 million people or whatever it was out on the streets celebrating.
500万人或其他什么人在街上庆祝
4 million people on the streets...
400万人涌上街头……
Could of been 10, could of been 20, you never know, but,
可能是1000万，可能是2000万，你永远不知道，但是
Messi winning the World Cup,
Messi赢得了世界杯
scoring two goals in the final,
在决赛中打进两球
in Summer.
在夏天
All the planets aligned into a perfect moment.
所有的行星都排列成一个完美的时刻
And I think it’s the best story
我认为这是你能写出的
that you could write about a football game ever.
关于一场足球比赛的最好的故事